# Joseph J. Fogarty

49 Pear Tree Lane Franklin Park NJ, 08823 908-510-2951 jjf1295@gmail.com josephfogarty.github.io

# SUMMARY

Fifth-year graduate student enrolled in the department of Civil and Environmental Engineering (CEE) at Princeton University, conducting research in the Environmental Fluid Mechanics (EFM) group. Although my undergraduate studies were in meteorology, my interests have pivoted from traditional operational forecasting to data-driven fluid dynamics and climate change. As a graduate student, my thesis employs numerical, statistical, and observational tools to simulate the changing Arctic sea ice surface and overlying atmosphere in the face of anthropogenic warming.

# EDUCATION

**Princeton University** 

Princeton, NJ

Ph.D. in Civil and Environmental Engineering

2018-Current

- Advisor: Elie Bou-Zeid
- $-\,$  M.A. in Civil and Env. Eng. Earned Apr 2021

#### **Rutgers University**

New Brunswick, NJ

B.S. in Meteorology, summa cum laude

2014-2018

- Advisor: Mark Miller
- Minors in Mathematics and Environmental Sciences

# RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

#### Ice-Water-Air Exchanges in the Marginal Ice Zone: Numerical

Simulations of Satellite-Sensed Surface States

Denver, CO

Oral Presentation at the Annual AMS Conference

2023

#### Turbulence-Resolving Simulations of Atmosphere-Surface Coupling

in the Marginal Ice Zone: The Interacting Effects of Temperature Heterogeneity Phoenix, AZ

Oral Presentation at the Annual APS-DFD Conference 2021

Nonlinearity of Air-Ice-Water Exchanges: Simulations of

Remotely-Sensed Surface States

San Francisco, CA

Poster Presentation at the Annual AGU Conference

2019

Modeling of Air-Sea-Ice Coupling of the Arctic Atmospheric Boundary Layer Princeton, NJ

Poster Presentation for CEE 509: Directed Research

2019

Drizzle Evaporation in the Stratocumulus-Topped Marine Boundary

Layer and its Relationship with Sub-Cloud Turbulence

New Brunswick, NJ

Oral Presentation for George H. Cook Honors Project

2018

Seasonal Trends in Extreme Minimum Temperatures at Six

New Jersey Locations

Piscataway, NJ

Poster Presentation at Rutgers Climate Symposium

2017

## TEACHING

• Assistant in Instruction at Princeton University Hydrology: Water and Climate (CEE 306) Spring 2022, Spring 2023

• Assistant in Instruction at Princeton University Environmental Fluid Mechanics (CEE 305) Fall 2021, Fall 2019

- Assistant in Instruction at Princeton University

Fall 2020, Fall 2022

The Climatological, Hydrological, & Environmental Footprints of Cities (CEE 474)

2016-2017

• Rutgers Learning Center Tutor at Rutgers University Pre-Calculus, Calculus, Linear Algebra

# SCHOLARSHIPS AND AWARDS

• Gordon S. Wu Scholarship

2018-Current

• Rutgers Dean's List

2014-2018

• Meteorology Student of the Year

2018

# **PROJECTS**

More details of projects on github.com/josephfogarty

• Ice SUrface energy Budget Solver (Python, 2019)

 $\it IceSUBS$  was a program written to solve a surface energy budget of a sea ice surface with eventual implementation in a large-eddy simulation model

• Forecast Verification (Python/Jupyter, 2017)

A Jupyter notebook created with the intention to explore techniques and libraries in Python relevant to data science, using forecast verification techniques as the motivation

## SKILLS

• Languages: Python, MATLAB

• Version Control: Git

• GIS: ARcGIS Pro, QGIS

• LATEX, Microsoft Office

#### Professional Experience

#### Office of the New Jersey State Climatologist

Piscataway, NJ

Undergraduate Intern

2017-2018

- Regular quality control for CoCoRaHS
- Synthesized national snow data for the 2016 Annual Snow Report
- Conducted independent research projects under the advice of the State Climatologist

#### **Rutgers Environmental Sciences**

New Brunswick, NJ

 $Weather\ Observer$ 

2016-2018

- Conduct and record daily weather observations few days per week
- Organize other volunteers in the program by creating weekly schedules

Spot-On Weather
Undergraduate Intern

Marlboro, NJ
2016

- Handled operational forecasts for TV and film crews

- Created forensic meteorology reports by using archival data for civil lawsuits

Page 2 of 2